A Guide to the Crystal Spring Study Club Records, 1955-2009
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Crystal Spring Study Club Records, 1955-2009
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 309
3 boxes.
The Crystal Spring Study Club
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Carole Robinson in 2014.
Historical Information
The Crystal Spring Knoll Study Group was formed in 1955 for women in the Crystal Spring Knoll neighborhood; the first meeting was on September 29, 1955. At some point the name changed to the Crystal Spring Study Club. The group started as a reading and discussion group but eventually it became a social outlet for these neighborhood women. Meetings were held on the third Thursday of the month from September to May. The December gathering was a holiday party and the May meeting was a luncheon in which officers were chosen for the next year.
Scope and Content
Record Group 309 holds the records of the Crystal Springs Study Club. The records date from 1955 to 2009, with the bulk of the materials dating 1955-1974 and then 1981-1998. Series 1 originally came in a binder and contains minutes, membership lists, membership attendance, by-laws and correspondence. Series 2 is a history of the club written by in 1977 by members Mary Jo Conner and Irene Young. Series 3 contains photographs which date 1970-1995. These photographs were originally in albums with identifying information written on the margins. Many of these photographs are in color.
Arrangement
RG 309 was originally donated in two bankers boxes, one filled with binders and one with photograph albums. The binders with administrative material make up Series 1. The binder that housed a history of the club made up Series 2; three other albums contained photographs which formed Series 3.
Records from binders were kept in the order in which they were donated and files labeled the same. Meeting minutes were often divided into separate file folders by the archivist for size considerations. If the meeting date was missing, the third Thursday date was put in brackets. For example, if the minutes said the February 1956 meeting, February [16], 1956 was indicated. Organization is by school year (September through May) rather than by calendar year.
Series 2, Club History, was photocopied as the papers were difficult to remove from the magnetic photo pages.
The photographs in Series 3 were removed from three photograph albums and placed in protective sleeves. Names were written on the back of the photographs by the archivist if indicated in the photograph album. Some names in brackets [ ] were added by the archivist. Most of the pictures are in chronological order. Some pictures, found after numbering had been completed, have higher numbers but were placed in the folders with the correct event.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
RG 49, Woman's Club of Lyon Village
Related Material
RG 50, Records of the Women's Club of Waycroft
Related Material
RG 73, Williamsburg Woman's Club of Arlington
Related Material
RG 93, Clarenford Woman's Club
Related Material
RG 96, The Lyon Park Woman's Club Record
Related Material
RG 98, Ki-Wives of Arlington, Virginia
Related Material
RG 322, Woman's Club of Arlington
Index Terms
Subjects:
Book clubs (Discussion groups); Women in community organization; Women -- United States -- Societies and clubs.; Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Records of the Meetings
  - 1955-1974
    - Minutes, September 19, 1955 - April 16, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, September 17, 1959 - May 27, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, September 21, 1967 - April [18], 1974 (Box 1)
    - Membership Attendence, 1955-1973 (Box 1)
    - Hostesses, 1955-1961 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, Executive Board, June 23, 1969 - August 28, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Programs, 1961-1962 and 1965-1970 (Box 1)
    - Officers, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Bylaws, 1959-1967 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous notes [n.d.] (Box 1)
  - 1974-1976
    - Minutes, November [21], 1974 - April 29, 1976 (Box 1)
  - 1976-1981
    - Minutes, September 16, 1976 - May 16, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Membership lists, 1976-1981 (Box 1)
  - 1981-1983
    - Minutes, September 17, 1981 - May 20, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Membership, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - By-Laws, October 18, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Letter sent to membership, March 8, 1982 (Box 1)
  - 1983-1991
    - Minutes, September 15, 1983 - May 16, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, September 11, 1987 - September 19, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Membership, 1983-1991 (Box 1)
    - Minues, Executive Board, May 24, 1983 - July 29, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Membership lists, 1981-1990 (Box 1)
    - Cards and Letters, September 10, 1985 - November 16, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Member Participation, 1973-1983 (Box 1)
    - Bylaws, November 1975 - October 17, 1988 (Box 1)
  - 1991-1998
    - Membership/Attendance, 1991-1998 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, September 19, 1991 - April 20, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, September 21, 1995 - April 16, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Membership, 1993-1998 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, Executive Committee, September 12, 1986 - August 10, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Cards, 1991-1998 (Box 1)
    - Letters, August 16, 1990 - February 24, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Membership Participation, 1981-1998 (Box 2)
    - Bylaws, September 24, 1989 - September 20, 1996 (Box 2)
  - 1998-2002
    - Minutes, September 17, 1998 - November 21, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Attendance, 1998-2002 (Box 2)
    - Membership, 1998-2002 (Box 2)
    - Letters and Cards, January 17, 1987 - April 19, 2005 (Box 2)
    - Bylaws, September 18, 1998 - October 22, 1999 (Box 2)
- Club History
  - "History of the Crystal Spring Study Club," 1977, 2009 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - 1970-1976 (Box 3)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 3)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - 1981-1984 (Box 3)
  - 1985-1987 (Box 3)
  - 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - 1990 (Box 3)
  - 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - 1995 (Box 3)